No!
'Passengers for flight 841020,
please go to Gate 7.
'Flight 784 to San Francisco
is now ready for boarding at...'
'Inmate number 87645:
Cole, James.
'27631: Johnson.'
Jose... Psst!
Jose, what's going on?
Bad news, man.
- Volunteers?
- Yeah. And they said your name.
Hey, maybe they'll give you
a pardon, man.
Yeah. That's why none
of the volunteers come back.
They all get a pardon.
- Some come back, I heard.
- Yeah...
Put me back! Let me go!
I didn't volunteer!
They got them
up on the seventh floor.
They hide them up there.
They're all messed up in the head,
brains don't work.
You don't know they're all messed up.
Nobody's seen them.
That's a rumour.
Nobody knows that. I don't believe that.
Good luck, man.
- Volunteer duty!
- I didn't volunteer.
You causing trouble again?
No. No trouble.
'These are the instructions
for the first-time probe.
'Listen carefully.
They must be followed exactly.
'All openings of your garment
must be sealed completely.
'If the integrity of the suit
is compromised in any way,
'if the fabric is torn
or a zipper not closed,
'readmittance will be denied.'
'If there are any indications
of contamination by germs,
'the subject will be denied re-entry
into the secure population.'
'Please place blood sample
in receptacle provided.'
'There will be
socialisation classes at 07:00
'for citizens cited
for deviations 23A and 96A,
'per sub-chapter six
of the Permanent Emergency Code.'
James Cole,
clear from quarantine.
Thank you. You two wait outside.
He's got a history, Doctor.
Violence.
Anti-social Six. Repeated violations
of the Permanent Emergency Code.
Insolence, defiance,
disregard of authority.
Doing 25 to life.
I don't think he's going to hurt us.
You aren't going to hurt us,
are you, Mr Cole?
No, sir.
Why don't you sit down, Mr Cole?
We appreciate your volunteering.
You're a very good observer, Cole.
Thank you.
We have a very advanced
programme, something very different.
An opportunity to reduce
your sentence considerably.
And possibly play an important role
in returning the human race
to the surface of the earth.
We want tough-minded people.
Strong mentally.
We've had some misfortunes with...
unstable types.
For a man in your position,
an opportunity.
Not to volunteer could be a real mistake.
Definitely a mistake.
Yet, among the myriad microwaves,
the infra-red messages,
the gigabytes of ones and zeros,
we find words, byte-sized now,
tinier even than science,
lurking in some vague electricity.
But if we but listen,
we hear the solitary voice
of that poet telling us...
Yesterday,
this day's madness did prepare...
...tomorrow's silence, triumph or despair.
Drink! For you know not
whence you came nor why.
why you go, nor where.
He was wandering around
in underpants
and one of those plastic,
see-through ladies' raincoats.
They ask the guy real nice
for some kinda ID.
He gets agitated,
starts screaming about viruses.
Totally irrational, totally disoriented.
Doesn't know where he is,
what day of the week it is.
All they got was his name.
Course they figure he's stoned,
some kinda psychotic episode.
- He's been tested for drugs?
- Negative for drugs.
But he took on five cops
like he was dusted to the eyeballs.
No drugs, if you believe that.
- He's in restraints.
- Weren't you listening?
I got two police officers in the hospital.
Yeah, he's in restraints.
The medic gave him enough Stelazine
to kill a horse.
Look at him. Raring to go.
That would explain the bruises,
I guess. The struggle.
Yeah. You wanna go in there?
Examine him? What?
Yes, please.
Is this all you have?
You ran it through your system?
No match-up, no licence, no prints,
no warrants. Nothing.
I should probably go in there
with you.
No, thank you.
That won't be necessary.
All right.
He'll be right here, just in case.
Mr Cole, my name is Kathryn Railly.
I'm a psychiatrist.
I work for the County,
I don't work for the police,
so my concern is for your well-being,
do you understand that?
Need to go! Need to go!
I can't make the police let you go.
But I do wanna help you.
So I... I need you to tell me
exactly what happened tonight.
Do you think you can do that, James?
May I call you James?
James
Nobody ever calls me that.
Have you been a patient at County...?
- Have I seen you some place?
- Not possible.
I need to go! I need to...
I'm supposed
to be gathering information!
- What kind of information?
- Won't help you.
Won't help anyone.
Won't change anything.
James, do you know
why you're here?
Cos I'm a good observer.
- I have a tough mind.
- I see.
You don't remember assaulting
a police officer? Several...
Why am I chained?
Why are there chains on me?
You've been in an institution before,
haven't you?
- A hospital?
- No. I need to go! Need to go!
- Have you been in prison, James?
- Underground.
Hiding?
I love this air.
Oh, such wonderful air!
What's wonderful about the air,
James?
Very fresh. No germs.
Why... why do you think
there aren't any germs in the air?
- This is October, right?
- April.
- What year is this?
- What year do you think it is?
1996.
That's the future, James.
Do you think you're living in the future?
1996 is the past.
No, 1996 is the future.
This is 1990.
Shut up, ladies.
- Where are you taking me?
- South of France, buddy. You'll love it.
I can't go to the South of France.
I need to make a telephone call.
Yeah, yeah. Zip it. You fooled the shrink
but you don't fool us. Come on.
Let's go, Ace.
Come on.
Come on, come on.
There you go.
Now, let me see your head, Jimbo.
See if you got any creepy-crawlies.
I need to make a telephone call.
Take it up with the doctor, Jimbo.
No calls till the doctor says.
- It's very important.
- What you gotta do, Jimbo...
...is take it easy,
relax into things.
We'll all get along fine
if you just relax.
'Wow! Whoo!
Let's go. Come on. Let's go.
Hey, Goines!
Yo, Goines!
Yo, Jeffrey!
- Goines!
- What?
Hey, look here.
This here's James.
Now, do me a favour,
show him around,
tell him the TV rules,
show him the games, OK?
How much you gonna pay me?
I'd be doing your job.
$5,000, my man. That enough?
- 5,000?
- I'll wire it to your account as usual.
$5,000! $5,000!
$5,000.
I'll give him the deluxe hospital tour.
- My man!
- Kid around, make him feel good.
You're the prisoners.
No, you're the guards!
- Now you got it.
- Alright, alright. OK, OK.
It's all in good fun.
Here's some games here.
And there's...
Get out! Get out!
He was in my chair.
Games, games.
Here's some games.
Games that wanna get out. Ha!
See? More games.
Games... they vegetise you.
See? Ah!
If you play the games,
you're voluntarily taking a tranquiliser.
I guess they gave you
chemical restraints? Drugs!
What did they give you?
Thorazine? Haldol? How much?
Learn your drugs, know your doses.
It's elementary.
I need to make a telephone call.
Telephone call? That's communication
with the outside world.
Doctor's discretion. Uh-uh. Nah!
If all of these nuts
could make phone calls,
it could spread, insanity oozing
through telephone cables,
oozing into the ears of all these
poor, sane people, infecting them.
Wackos everywhere,
plague of madness.
In fact, Jim... very few of us
here are actually mentally ill.
I'm not saying you're not mentally ill.
For all I know, you're... crazy as a loon.
But that's not why you're here.
It's not why you're here!
You're here because of the system.
There's the television.
It's all right there.
All right there.
Look, listen, kneel, pray.
Commercials!
We're not productive any more.
Nobody needs to make things.
It's all automated.
What are we for, then?
We're consumers, Jim.
OK, buy a lot of stuff,
you're a good citizen.
But if you don't buy a lot of stuff,
what are you, then? What?
Mentally ill.
Fact, Jim, fact!
If you don't buy things,
toilet paper, new cars, blenders,
electrically-operated sexual devices,
stereo systems
with brain-implanted headphones,
screwdrivers with built-in radar,
voice-activated computers...
Take it easy, Jeffrey. Be calm.
Right. That's right.
You're a very attractive woman. Ha!
If you wanna watch
a particular television program,
you go to the charge nurse
and tell her the day and time.
But you have to tell her
before the show is on.
There's this guy who always requested
shows that had already played.
Yes! No!
You have to tell her before.
He couldn't grasp the idea that
the nurse couldn't make it be yesterday.
Couldn't turn back time,
thank you, Einstein! Now he was nuts!
- He was a fruitcake...
- OK, that's it, Jeffrey.
You're gonna get a shot.
I warned you.
Right. Right. Right.
I got a little carried away
explaining the inner workings
of the institution to Jim.
I don't really come from outer space.
I J Washington.
He doesn't come from outer space.
- Don't mock me, my friend.
- Ha-ha!
Get out of my chair!
It's a condition of mental divergence.
I find myself on the planet Ogo,
part of an intellectual elite,
preparing to subjugate
the barbarian hordes on Pluto.
But even though this is a totally
convincing reality for me in every way,
nevertheless, Ogo is actually
a construct of my psyche.
I am mentally divergent
in that I am escaping
certain unnamed realities
that plague my life here.
When I stop going there,
I will be well.
Are you also divergent, friend?
This is a place for crazy people.
I'm not crazy.
We don't use that term "crazy", Mr Cole.
Well, you've got some
real nuts here.
I know some things that you don't know.
It's gonna be very difficult
for you to understand it.
- Hey! Hey!
- I'm not gonna...
I'm not gonna hurt anyone.
Alright.
Look, have any of you heard
of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
They stencil this on the sides
of buildings everywhere.
- Have you seen this?
- Mr Cole...
Have you seen this?
Why don't you just take your time
and try to explain it from the beginning?
Right. It's 1990.
OK. That makes sense.
They wouldn't have been active yet.
OK.
OK!
Five billion people died
in 1996 and 1997.
Almost the entire population
of the world.
Only about 1% of us survived.
Are you going to save us, Mr Cole?
How can I save you?
This already happened.
I can't save you. Nobody can.
I am simply trying
to gather information
to help the people in the present
trace the path of the virus.
We're not in the present now,
Mr Cole?
No. 1990 is the past.
This already happened.
- That's what I'm trying...
- Mr Cole? Mr Cole...
You believe 1996 is the present, then?
Is that it?
No, 1996 is the past too.
Listen to me. What I...
What I...
What I need to do
is make a telephone call.
I can straighten this all out
if I make a telephone call.
Who would you call?
Who would straighten everything out?
- The scientists.
- Oh.
They'll wanna know
that they sent me to the wrong time.
I can leave a voice mail message
that they monitor from the present.
Can I just make
one telephone call, please?
Please?
What are you doing in the dog bowl?
Who put those Doritos in there?
Yes? What?
Voice mail? I don't know what you
Will you stop making that noise?
I don't know
what you're talking about.
Is this a joke?
I don't know any scientists.
Get out of... James who?
It wasn't who you expected?
No. It was some lady.
- She didn't know anything.
- Well...
Maybe it was the wrong number.
No. That's why they chose me,
I remember things.
James, where did you grow up?
Dr Railly...
I have the strangest feeling
that I've met you before.
Wait. This is 1990. I'm supposed
to be leaving messages in 1996!
It's not the right number yet.
That's the problem!
'Listen to me.'
'I have a message for them!'
No!
Won't work. Can't open it.
You think you can remove the grille.
But you can't, it's welded.
See? Told you.
And all the doors are locked too.
They're protecting people
on the outside from us,
when the people on the outside
are as crazy as us.
Do you know what crazy is?
Crazy is "majority rules". Yeah. Huh!
- Take germs, for example.
- Germs?
Uh-huh. In the 18th century,
no such thing. Nada, nothing.
No one ever imagined such a thing.
No sane person, anyhow.
Along comes this doctor...
Ah, ah, ah...
Semmelweis!
Semmelweis.
Semmelweis comes along
and he's trying to convince people,
well, other doctors mainly,
that there's teeny invisible
bad things called germs
that get into your body
and make you sick. Uh?
He's trying to get doctors
to wash their hands.
"What is this guy? Crazy?
- "Teeny, tiny, invisible - what'd he call them?
- Germs? What?"
Now, cut to the 20th century.
Last week, right before I got dragged
into this hellhole...
...I go in to order a burger
in this fast-food joint.
The guy drops it on the floor.
Jim, he picks it up, he wipes it off,
he hands it to me like it was all OK.
"What about the germs?" I say.
He says, "I don't believe in germs.
"Germs are just a plot they made up
to sell you disinfectants and soaps."
Now, he's crazy, right? See?
There's no right, there's no wrong.
There's only popular opinion.
You... you... you...
you believe in germs, right?
I'm not crazy.
Of course not.
You want to escape, right?
That's very sane. That's very sane.
I can help you.
You want me to, don't you? Get you out.
You know how to get out of here?
Yes, my son.
- Then why don't you?
- Why don't I try to escape?
Good question, very good question.
Intelligent.
Because I would be crazy to escape.
I have sent out word.
- I am taken care of.
- What does that mean?
I managed to contact
certain underlings, evil spirits,
secretaries of secretaries
and other assorted minions,
who will contact my father.
And when my father finds out
I'm in this kind of place,
he'll have them transfer me
to one of those classy joints,
where they treat you properly
like a person, like a guest!
- With sheets and towels like a big hotel.
- Shh!
With great drugs for all us nutcase,
lunatic, maniac devils! Ha!
Sorry. Uh, sorry.
I got a little agitated.
The thought of escape had crossed
my mind and suddenly... suddenly...
Suddenly, I felt like bending
the fucking bars back,
and ripping out the goddamn
window frames and eating them!
Yes, eating them!
Leaping, leaping, leaping!
Colonics for everyone!
Alright! You dumb assholes,
I'm a mental patient.
I'm supposed to act out.
Wait till you morons find out who I am.
My father's gonna be really upset,
and when he gets upset,
the ground shakes!
My father is God!
I worship my father!
'These dramatic video tapes,
'secretly obtained
by animal rights activists,
'have aroused public indignation.
'But many scientists
vehemently disagree...'
Torture. Experiments.
We're all monkeys.
They hurt you?
Not as bad as what they're doing
to the Easter Bunny. Ha-ha.
Look at them.
They're just asking for it.
'Animals inside the lab are fed...'
Maybe the human race
deserves to be wiped out.
Wiping out the human race?
It's a great idea. It's great!
But more of a long-term thing.
First, we have to focus
on more immediate goals.
I didn't say a word
about you-know-what.
What are you talking about?
Your plan, emancipation.
What are you writing?
- Are you a... a reporter?
- It's private.
- A law suit?
- Gonna sue them?
- Yo, Jimbo. Time for your meds.
'Take a chance. Live the moment.
'Sunshine, gorgeous beaches...
the Florida Keys!'
'We'll return to the Marx Brothers
in "Monkey Business".'
Monkey business! Huh!
Monkey business!
Fetch!
Get it?
Monkey. Mon... key.
Monk... key!
What?
'If you see a bearish future
in the decade ahead,
'consider the changes
sweeping the world
'and the opportunities they offer.'
And the opportunities they offer.
Ooh, they really dosed you, Jim. Ugh!
Huh! Major load.
Danger, Will Robinson. Danger.
You gotta get it together.
Focus! Focus! Focus!
Remember the plan. I did my part!
- What?
- Shh!
- Not "what". When!
- When?
Yes. When. Now. Now, Jim.
Now! Yes! Now! Buy! Sell!
Stocks! Bonds! Pensions! Sell! Yes!
No more monkey business!
- No... more...
- I'm getting dizzy.
- ...monkey business!
- Make him stop!
$500! I got $500! I'm insured!
Yeah! A window of opportunity
is opening now.
Now's the time for all you men
to seize the moment!
The moment! Now's the time
for all you men to seize the day!
- A-ha!
- Quit playing the fool!
Mastercard! Visa!
The key to happiness!
Jim, seize the moment!
- Jeffrey! Come back here!
- For God's sake!
A-ha! Go. Jim!
- Get out. Out!
- Come here! Jeffrey! Jeffrey!
The future can be yours!
Last chance! Last chance!
Last chance! Last...
Ow! Stop!
The best place to go would be Florida.
The Keys are lovely this time of year.
Two's not working today.
Use one.
I've tried everything.
He's not responding to treatment.
And I just feel that we're wasting...
Kathryn, this was in my box,
but I suspect it wasn't meant for me.
"You are the most bootiful woman
I have ever seen.
"You live in a bootiful world
but you don't know it.
"You have freedom, sun... shine,
air you can breathe."
James Cole, right?
"I would do anything to stay here,
but I must leave. Please help me."
OK, OK, OK.
- Poor man.
- Hey, Kathryn.
James Cole is one of yours, right?
He eloped.
Last seen, he was up on two.
Shit!
We have to know exactly what's there.
Doctor, we have a visitor.
Erm... may I help you? Excuse me.
May I help you? Excuse me.
Excuse me!
Hey, Jimbo. What's up, man?
OK, Jimbo.
Alright, it's OK. Take it easy.
- We'll work this out, OK?
- Take it easy.
We'll work this out, OK?
We'll take you back to your room
and give you cookies...
- You're gonna be alright, man.
- OK? All right, buddy?
- No, no!
- Come on, calm down!
Drag him down!
Drag him the fuck down! Crazy fuck!
I'm not trying to hurt anyone.
Dr Railly, help me, please!
- I'll give you something to calm you.
- No more drugs! No more drugs!
You're very confused.
- Get him in there.
- You don't understand!
Get off me! Get off me!
Four years, Kathryn, we've been
working together for four years,
and I've never seen you like this before.
So please stop being so defensive.
This isn't an inquisition.
I didn't think I was being defensive,
I was trying to explain to you exactly...
He should've been in restraints.
It was bad judgement on your part,
plain and simple. Why not own up to it?
OK, it was bad judgement, but I have
the strangest feeling about him.
I've seen him some place...
Two policemen are already in hospital.
Now we've got a security guard
with a skull fracture.
I said it was bad judgement!
What else do you want me to say?
Now, you see that?
You see what I mean?
You're being defensive.
Isn't she being defensive?
- Dr Fletcher.
- What?
Er... we have a...
another situation.
He was fully restrained
and the door was locked?
- Yes, sir. I did it myself.
- Hmm...
And he was fully sedated?
He was fully sedated.
Then are you trying to tell me
a fully sedated, fully restrained patient
somehow slipped out that vent,
replaced the grille behind him
and is wriggling his way
through the ventilation system?
Watch it!
'You sure fucked up!'
- Where are you?
- 'Ah, you can talk.
'What did you do, Bobby boy, volunteer?'
- My name's not Bob.
- 'Not a prob, Bob.
'Where did they send you?'
- Where are you?
- 'Another cell.
'Maybe.'
What do you mean, "maybe"?
What's that supposed to mean?
""Maybe" means
maybe I'm in the next cell.
'Another "volunteer", like you.
'Or maybe I'm in the central office,
'spying on you
for all those science bozos.
'Or hey, maybe I'm not even here.
'Maybe I'm just in your head.
'No way to confirm anything.
'Where did they send you?'
- 1990.
- '90? How was it?
'Good drugs? Lots of pussy?
'Hey, Bob, did you do the job?
'Did you find out the "big info"?
'Army of the Twelve Monkeys?'
It was supposed to be 1996.
'Science ain't an exact science
with these clowns.
'But they're getting better.
'You're lucky you didn't end up
in Ancient Egypt!
'Shh! They're coming.'
'The Freedom for Animals Association
'is the secret headquarters
of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
'They are the ones
who are going to do it.
'I can't do any more.
I have to go now.
'Have a Merry Christmas!'
- Well?
- What?
Did you or did you not
record that message?
It's a reconstruction
of a deteriorated recording.
Weak signal on our number.
We have to put them together
one word at a time like jigsaw puzzles.
We just finished rebuilding this.
Did you or did you not make this call?
I couldn't make any call.
You sent me to the wrong year.
It was 1990.
1990?
- You're certain of that?
- What did you do with your time, Cole?
- Did you waste it on drugs? Women?
- They forced me to take drugs!
Forced you? Why would someone
force you to take drugs?
I... I was in trouble.
I got arrested. I...
I did what you wanted.
I got a specimen of a spider.
But I didn't have any place
to put it, so I ate it.
But you sent me to the wrong year,
so it doesn't matter.
- Did you see this when you went back?
- No, sir. I don't think so.
What about these people?
Did you see any of these people?
No. No...
Oh, wait. Wait.
Him? You saw that man?
Maybe in the...
maybe in the mental institution.
You were in a mental institution?
Oh, God!
Cole, you were sent back
to make very important observations.
You could've made
a real contribution.
- Helped to reclaim the planet.
- As well as reducing your sentence.
The question is, Cole,
do you want another chance?
Good.
Last connection going on.
Stand clear, please.
- He's your choice.
- Nothing we can do about that now.
No mistakes this time, Cole.
Stay alert. Keep your eyes open.
Good thinking about the spider, Cole.
Try and do something like that again.
Just relax now. Don't fight it.
We're sending you to the third quarter
of 1996, right on the money.
What? I don't understand!
Where am I?
I gotta find them! I gotta find them!
Help me!
I don't know where I am!
- You gotta help me find them!
- Jose?
- Jose!
- Cole!
Where are we, Cole?
Where are we?
- Jose!
- Cole! Help me!
Wait!
'"In a season of great pestilence,
'"there are omens and divinations.'
"And one of the four beasts
gave unto the seven angels
"" seven golden vials
full of the wrath of God
"who liveth forever and ever."
Revelations.
In the 14th century, according
to the local accounts of that time,
this man appeared suddenly
in the village of Wyle near Stonehenge
in April of 1362.
Using unfamiliar words
and speaking in a strange accent,
the man made dire prognostications
about a pestilence
which he said would wipe out humanity
in approximately 600 years.
Obviously this doomsday scenario
is considerably more compelling
when reality supports it
with a virulent disease,
whether it's the bubonic plague,
smallpox or AIDS.
And now we have
technological horrors as well,
such as chemical warfare
which first reared its ugly head
during the deadly mustard gas attacks
of World War I.
During such an attack
in the French trenches in October, 1917,
we have an account of this soldier
who was wounded by shrapnel
and hospitalised
apparently in a state of hysteria.
Doctors found that he had lost
all comprehension of French
but that he spoke English fluently,
albeit in a regional dialect
they didn't recognise.
The man, though physically unaffected
by the gas, was beside himself.
He claimed that he had come
from the future,
that he was looking for a pure germ
that would ultimately wipe mankind
off the face of the earth,
starting in the year 1996.
Though injured, the young soldier
disappeared from the hospital,
no doubt trying to warn others
and substituting for the agony of war
a self-inflicted agony
we call the Cassandra complex.
Cassandra, in Greek Legend,
was condemned to know the future,
but to be disbelieved
when she foretold it.
Hence, the agony of foreknowledge
combined with the impotence
to do anything about it.
I'm going right out to get vaccinated.
Hi.
I think, Dr Railly, you've given
the alarmists a bad name.
- I have?
- Mm-hm.
Surely there's convincing data
that the planet cannot survive
the excesses of the human race.
This is true.
Proliferation of atomic devices,
uncontrolled breeding habits,
pollution of land, sea and air,
the rape of the environment.
Isn't it obvious that Chicken Little
represents the sane vision
and that Homo sapiens' motto,
"Let's go shopping",
is the cry of the true lunatic?
- Dr Railly...
- Kathryn, I'll see you later.
Please, Dr Railly, I wonder
if you're aware of my own studies...
See you at work tomorrow!
Get in the car!
Get in the car! I've got a gun.
Get in the car.
Go on, drive.
Take my purse.
I got cash, credit cards... Take my keys.
- Start the car!
- OK.
No!
Here. Turn right. Turn right here.
- Where are we going?
- Philadelphia.
- That's more than 100 miles.
- That's why I can't walk there.
Just let me go.
- Just drive!
- You can take the car.
I don't know how to drive.
I went underground when I was eight,
I told you that before.
At the next...
At the next corner, turn right.
Cole. James Cole.
You escaped from a locked room
six years ago.
Six years for you.
- Turn around. Get going!
- OK.
I can't believe that this is a coincidence,
Mr Cole.
Have you been following me?
You said you would help me.
I know this isn't what you meant but...
I don't have any money.
I hurt my leg
and I've been sleeping on the street.
I'm sure I smell bad.
Do you have any food in this car?
You have been following me,
haven't you?
No.
No, I... I saw this.
In a... in a store window.
- I can read, remember?
- Uh-huh.
Why do you wanna go to Philadelphia?
I checked out the Baltimore information.
It was nothing.
It's in Philadelphia.
That's where they are,
the ones who did it.
The Twelve Monkeys.
Is that a radio?
Can you... turn it on?
'This is a personal message to you.
'Are you at the end of your rope?
'Are you dying to get away?
'The Florida Keys are waiting for you.
Ocean waves...'
I've never seen the ocean.
It's an advertisement, Mr Cole.
What?
It's an advertisement.
You do understand that, don't you?
It's not really a special message to you.
"Mr Cole"?
- You used to call me James.
- You prefer that?
James, uh...
you don't really have a gun...
Can you turn this up?
Can you make this louder?
Oh, I love the music of the 20th century!
Oh, I love this air!
I love to breathe this air! Oh! Ha-ha!
'WXBX Newsbreak.
News as it happens.
'A story breaking right now is emergency
crews are converging in a cornfield
'where playmates of nine-year-old
Ricky Neuman saw him disappear.
'Young Neuman apparently stepped
into an abandoned well shaft
'and is lodged somewhere
in the 150-foot pipe.
'Possibly alive,
possibly seriously injured,
playmates claim he cried out...'
- Never cry wolf.
- What?
My father said that to me.
He said, "Never cry wolf."
Then people won't believe you
if something really happens.
If something really happens
like what, James?
Something bad.
Can we have more music?
I don't wanna hear this.
Can we hear more music?
Oh, that! That's good!
Yes, that's... that's good.
'Hello, Dr Railly?
This is Wickke from Psych Admitting.
'Do you remember James Cole,
'the paranoid who pulled the Houdini
back in '90?
'Well, he's back and he's...
OK, sorry about that.
'He's looking for you.
I thought you ought to know.
'Alright. Take care.'
It's just like I told you.
Me and my husband went ahead
and she never showed.
That is totally unlike her.
Do you happen to know
the make of her car?
Cherokee.
A '94 Cherokee, silver.
'Ach, Himmel! I have dood it!
'I have done dood it, ja!
'I, Professor Grozenschiffer, have
invented the time tunnel. Oh, boy!'
No!
'Now my time machine
is all ready for experiment.'
You were in my dream just now.
Your hair was different.
Different colour.
I'm sure it was you.
What was the dream about?
About an airport.
Before everything happened.
It's the same dream I always had...
when I was a kid.
And I was in it? What did I do?
You were very upset.
You're always very upset
in the dream.
I just never knew it was you.
It wasn't me before, James.
It's become me now
because of, er... what's happening.
Could you please untie me?
No, I think it was always you.
It's very strange.
You're flushed. And you were moaning.
I think you're running a fever.
What are you doing?
'In Fresno, California, crews continue
'to attempt to rescue
9-year-old Ricky Neuman.'
'Closer to home in Baltimore,
Kathryn Railly,
'prominent psychiatrist
and author of a book on insanity,
'disappeared mysteriously last night
after a lecture at the university.
'Former mental patient, James Cole,
is wanted for questioning
'regarding Dr Railly's disappearance.
'Authorities warn that
Cole has a history of violence,
'and advise anyone spotting him
to notify authorities at once.'
I love this music.
We don't have this.
We don't have anything like this.
What are all those?
- These?
- Mm.
My notes. Clues.
- What kind of clues?
- About the secret army.
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys
who spread the virus.
That's why I'm here.
I have to find them. That's my mission.
I have to locate them, because
they have the virus in its pure form,
before it mutates.
When I locate them, they'll send
a scientist back here to study the virus.
Then he and the rest of the scientists
will make a cure.
'...50 police officers, including
Special Tactical Unit Personnel,
'have now been mobilised to control
the growing thousands of onlookers
'here in Fresno, California,
as the rescue operation...'
- Does that disturb you?
- No.
Thought it was about us.
Thought maybe they'd captured us
and arrested me.
- Just a joke.
- Hmm.
I remember being very afraid
for that little boy.
All alone down that well, not knowing
if anybody's gonna get him out.
First time I was really afraid
when I was a kid.
What do you mean,
when you were a kid?
Never mind. It's just a prank, a hoax.
That boy's hiding in a barn.
"There are omens and divinations.
"One of the four beasts
gave unto the seven angels
"seven golden vials
full of the wrath of God
"who liveth forever and ever."
You won't think I'm crazy
when people start dying next month.
At first, they'll think
it's just some weird fever.
Then they'll find out. They'll catch on.
Wait! Stop here! Stop the car!
Stop! Right here!
I was right! They're here!
You see? Twelve Monkeys!
Twelve Monkeys!
Do you believe me now? Come on!
Come on!
They're here! You see?
Twelve Monkeys!
Twelve Monkeys. Come on!
See? Twelve Monkeys.
Wait. Wait.
Wait, here! Here. Do you see it?
You see?
I see some red paint, some marks.
Marks? You think that...?
- Oh, this is ridic...
- Hey! Hey!
Don't you... do anything crazy...
- I...
- Or I'll hurt somebody.
I'm not gonna do anything crazy!
None of this is what you think it is.
You can't hide from them, Bob.
I said, you can't hide from them.
No, sir, old Bob. Don't even try.
They hear everything.
They got that tracking device on you.
They can find you anywhere, anytime!
It's in the tooth. Right, Bob?
But I fooled them, old buddy.
They don't have to spy on me.
I'm doing what I'm supposed to be doing.
You see? Here it is again.
See? Here, follow this paint trail.
- Here. It's here, see?
- People coming!
- Here.
- I'm not going in there.
- No! Come with me!
- James...
The paint trail goes here.
Let go! Let go of my arm.
James, we shouldn't be here.
Goddamn it!
Let's get outta here.
James, we shouldn't be here!
Hey!
Please don't kill me!
Don't kill me! Please don't kill me!
You stick around, bitch.
Are you alright?
Is he alive?
Go on.
We're running out of time.
- You can't help him.
- Oh, Jesus! James, you killed him!
All I see are dead people.
Come on!
You never had a gun before!
I have one now.
Come on. Come on!
"...dragons in their pleasant palaces.
"The seventh angel poured out
his vial into the air,
"and there came..."
You!
You! You're one of us!
This is it. Come on.
Erm... can we help you?
It's just a tape.
I'm looking for the Army
of the Twelve Monkeys.
We don't know anything about
any Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
- So why don't you disappear?
- I just want some information.
- Didn't you hear me? I said...
- Don't hurt her!
Please! I'm a psychiatrist.
Just do whatever he tells you, OK?
He's disturbed. He's dangerous.
Please! Just cooperate.
You want money?
We only got a few bucks.
I told you what I want. Get down.
Lock that door. Lock it now!
I told you that fucking Goines
would get us into...
Shut up!
Goines?
Jeffrey Goines?
Jeffrey becomes a big star
and the media latch on to him,
because he's picketing his own father,
a famous Nobel-prize-winning virologist.
- You must've seen it on TV.
- I don't watch TV.
- Is this him?
- Yeah, that's him. That's him.
What are you gonna do to us?
Tell me more about Jeffrey.
Jeffrey started getting bored
with the shit we do,
picketing, leafleting,
letter-writing stuff.
He said we were
ineffectual, liberal jerk-offs.
He wanted to do guerrilla actions
in order to "educate the public".
Like this?
That's when he let a hundred snakes
loose in the Senate.
But we weren't into that stuff.
It's counter-productive, we told him.
So he and eleven guys, they split off
and formed this underground army.
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
You see?
They starting planning a human hunt.
They bought stun guns and nets
to trap lawyers and bankers.
They didn't do it, of course.
They didn't do any of it.
Like always,
Mr Big Shot sold his friends out.
What does that mean?
He goes on TV and
gives this big news conference.
Tells the world he realised his daddy's
experiments are vital for humanity
and that the use of animals
is absolutely necessary,
and from now on, Jeffrey Goines is
gonna personally supervise the labs
to make sure the little animals
aren't going to suffer.
What is this?
You can't just barge in on people.
It's not how the world works.
Just be quiet and drive the car.
I know what I'm doing.
Oh, no, you don't! This car is stolen.
OK? We are in big trouble.
Big trouble!
If you don't turn yourself
over to the police, they'll kill you,
and they'll shoot me
as an accessory to murder.
- You're all going to die.
- Nobody is going to die!
You're not going to save the world.
OK? You're delusional.
You've made all this up
out of bits and pieces in your head.
- No.
- Yes! Let me give you an example.
You and Jeffrey Goines were both
patients at County Hospital...
Jeffrey Goines was a fruitcake.
And he told you then that his father
was a famous scientist
who worked with viruses so you've
incorporated that into this fantasy...
He didn't say his father was a scientist,
he said his father was God.
This is insane!
'...prominent psychiatrist
and author, Dr Kathryn Railly,
'has been abducted by a dangerous
mental patient, James Cole.
'Cole was under Railly's care
six years ago when he escaped from...'
What is the matter with your leg?
- I got shot.
- Shot?
Who shot you?
I dunno. It was some kind of war.
Never mind.
You wouldn't believe me, anyway.
What are you doing?
- We don't need gas.
- I thought you didn't know how to drive.
I said I was too young to drive.
I didn't say I was stupid.
This can't go on.
If you have a bullet in your leg,
I have to take care of it.
I'm a doctor.
I need some supplies.
'Meanwhile
in Fresno, California
'mining engineers continue
their desperate attempt
'to sink a shaft parallel to the one
in which nine-year-old Ricky Neuman
'is believed trapped.
'Authorities say there's still a chance...'
You shouldn't put your weight on it.
You need stitches and antibiotics.
Lucky for you it's near the surface.
I love seeing the sun.
Wait!
Let me help you.
You smell so good.
You have to give yourself up.
You know that, don't you?
What are you doing...? James?
- I'm sorry.
- What are you doing?
James... Stop it!
What are you doing? Let go of me!
- Did they find him?
- Who?
- That kid, the one in the pipe.
- You believe that?
They're lowering a monkey down there
with a miniature infra-red camera
and a roast beef sandwich
wrapped up in tin foil.
- You're making it up.
- I shit you not, man.
Life is really weird.
A monkey and a roast beef sandwich!
Would that I could enjoy
this opulent dinner
and this most stimulating
and exciting company
for itself,
with no sense of purpose.
But, alas... I am burdened.
With all this excess of public attention
and cacophony of praise
there comes great responsibility.
I don't have to tell you all
that the dangers of science
are a time-worn threat.
From Prometheus stealing fire
from the gods...
What friend?
I'm not expecting anyone.
...to the Dr Strangelove terror,
but never before...
This is ridiculous!
My father is giving a major address.
...to fear the power...
we have at hand.
Normally, if we caught a guy
sneaking around like this with no ID,
we'd bust his ass.
'Scuse my French.
This one says he knows you.
Since you seemed to have had
a few unusual associates,
we certainly would not want to arrest
one of your closest pals.
Never seen him before in my life.
Feel free to torture this man
or whatever it is you do.
I'm going back to listen
to my father's very eloquent discourse...
I'm here about some monkeys.
- Monkeys?
- Monkeys. Yes.
Twelve of them.
Arnold... You look like shit.
- You know this man?
- Of course, I know this man.
Arnold Pettibone. Hmm...
Gee, Arnie, it's black tie.
I said drop by, but it's Dad's big do.
VIPs, senators, Secret Service...
You hungry, Arnie?
Real killer feast we're putting on tonight.
Lots of dead lamb, dead cow, dead pig.
Shall we?
Hi, how are you? Hello.
Very attractive.
"The Great Escape." 1990.
Watch it!
Huh? The County Hospital?
Am I right?
I can't do anything
about what you're going to do.
I can't change anything. I won't stop you.
I just want the information.
Come on.
Hi, ladies. Nice to see you again.
Watch your step on the way down.
- Alright, who blabbed? Bruhns? Weller?
- I just want access to the pure virus.
- Virus?
- Yes, for the future.
I need to know where it is
and exactly what it is.
I get it! I see what you're up to.
It's your old plan, isn't it?
What plan?
I don't know what you're talking about.
Yes, you do.
We were in the dayroom
watching television
and you were upset
about the desecration of the planet
but then you said, "Wouldn't it be great
if there was a virus
"that'd wipe out all of mankind,
like the animals and the trees?"
No. You're just trying to confuse me.
And I told you my father
was a famous virologist
and you said, "He could make a germ
and we could steal it." Go, go, right?
The thing mutates!
We live underground.
The world belongs
to the dogs and cats.
We live like worms.
I just need the information!
- Take it easy.
- You are a total nutcase!
Completely deranged!
Delusional! Paranoid!
Your processor's all fucked up! Ha!
Your information tray is jammed, man!
You know what it is,
the Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
It's a collection of space-case
do-gooders saving rainforests.
I have nothing to do
with those bozos any more.
I quit being the rich kid fall guy
for those ineffective bananas!
So much for your grand plot, asshole!
My father's been warning people
about the dangers
of experimentation
with DNA viruses for years!
You processed that information
through your paranoid brain,
and behold, a non-profit organisation
becomes some sinister,
revolutionary cabal!
This man is completely bat shit!
Ladies and gentlemen,
do you realise
where he thinks he comes from?
'Captain Dan Miller, the man
in charge of the rescue operation,
'says he has consulted with experts
and they assure us there will be no...'
If you ask me, the monkey's gonna eat
that goddamn sandwich himself.
Did a man just come
running through here?
'This is just in: Police say
the body of a woman
'found strangled in Knutson State Park
'could be kidnapping victim
Dr Kathryn Railly...'
Anybody see someone
come through here?
'...body was discovered
less than an hour ago by a hiker.
'But we have an unconfirmed report
that the victim,
'a woman in her late 20s or early 30s,
was savagely mutilated.
'Earlier in the day police located Railly's
abandoned car found not far from...'
Any sign of him?
Nothing.
He can't just disappear.
You bastard!
I could've died in there,
you son of a bitch!
What were you thinking of,
you twisted sack of shit?
I'm sorry.
Sorry I locked you in the trunk.
I'm sick of you!
What have you done?
Did you kill somebody?
Yes.
A million people.
Five billion people.
What?
Jeffrey Goines said that
it was my idea about the virus.
We were in the institution and
it was all so fuzzy with the drugs and all.
Do you think it was my idea?
Do you think maybe
I wiped out the human race?
Nobody is gonna wipe out
the human race!
Not you or Jeffrey or anybody else!
You've created something in your mind.
- Mentally divergent?
- Whatever!
A substitute reality...
because you don't wanna deal
with anything.
I would love it if that was true.
It can be dealt with,
but only if you want to. I can help you.
- Oh! They're after me. Come on.
- Who is after you?
I think there was some policemen
at that party.
Party? You went to a p...?
Never mind.
It's important you surrender instead
of them catching you running away.
Wouldn't it be great if I was crazy,
then the world would be OK?
- Give me the gun. Where's the gun?
- I lost it.
I could live right here.
You got water, air, stars...
- I'm gonna attract their attention.
- You can breathe.
I'll attract their attention.
Ha-ha! Oh, I love this world!
They'll tell you to put your hands
on your head. Do what they say.
And I love the frogs and spiders.
Remember, I'll be with you.
I'll help you.
I won't let them...
Then I said something about cooperating
and he said he would do that.
So I, erm... I got in the car...
Thanks.
And when I...
No, I started honking the horn,
and then when I got out,
he was gone.
I'll tell you something, you lucked out.
For a while, we thought
you were a body they found mutilated.
- He wouldn't do that.
- Is this the man he attacked?
I wanna be clear about this, OK?
This man and the other one
were severely beating us.
James Cole didn't start it.
In fact, he saved me.
Funny thing, Doctor,
maybe you can help explain it to me,
you being a psychiatrist and all.
Why is it that kidnap victims always
tell us about the guys that grab them?
And they try to make us understand
how kind these bastards really were.
It's a normal reaction
to a life-threatening situation.
He's sick. OK?
He thinks he comes from the future.
He's been living in a meticulously
constructed fantasy world
that's starting to disintegrate,
he needs help.
OK.
'Exhausted but apparently
unharmed by her 30-hour ordeal,
'Dr Railly returned to Baltimore
this morning
'without making a public statement.
'The author and psychiatrist is currently
in seclusion at her home.
'In the meantime, police have pieced
together a scenario of events
'that began with escaped
mental patient, James Cole...'
- Sorry.
- No, it's OK.
- I'm just hyperalert, I can't sleep.
- Well, did you take your sedative?
I hate those things.
They mess my head up. Uh-huh.
'...went on a rampage of violence.
'With the kidnapping
of the Baltimore woman,
'James Cole is now also wanted
'in connection with the brutal slaying
of Rodney Wiggins, an ex-convict...'
'His body was discovered
in an abandoned theatre,
'not far from where Cole left
three young animal rights activists...'
Oh, now do they really believe
he's gonna show up here? Please!
'And in Fresno, California...'
He's dead, isn't he? That little boy.
He's fine. It was just a prank
he and his friends pulled.
'...to rescue 9-year-old Ricky Neuman
from an abandoned mine shaft
'ended abruptly
when playmates confessed
'that Neuman's disappearance
was merely a prank
'and that in fact the missing child
was hiding in a nearby barn.'
Ba-ba-ba-doom, ba-ba-ba-doom.
- Congratulations, Cole.
- Wonderful.
Well done! Very well done!
During your interview
while you were under the influence,
you told us that you liked music.
- This isn't prison, James.
- This is a hospital.
Just until you recover your equilibrium.
- You're still a little disorientated.
- It is a stressful thing, time travel.
You stood up very well, considering.
You connected the Army
of the Twelve Monkeys
with the famous virologist and his son.
- Others will take over now.
- We'll retake the planet.
- This is it, James, what you worked for.
- A full pardon.
- You'll be out in no time.
- Women will want to know you.
I don't want your women!
I wanna get well!
And you will be well, James.
Soon.
You people don't exist.
You're not real.
We can't travel back in time.
Whoop, whoop. Uh-uh.
You're not here.
You can't trick me.
You're in my mind!
I am insane,
and you are my insanity.
He not only used the word "prank",
he said the boy was hiding in a barn.
Kathryn, Kathryn... he kidnapped you.
You saw him murder somebody.
You knew there was a real possibility
that he could kill you too.
You were under tremendous
emotional stress.
Oh, for God's sake, Owen,
listen to me.
He knew about the boy in Fresno
and he says five billion people
are gonna die!
No way he could possibly
know that. Kathryn!
You're a rational person,
you're a trained psychiatrist.
You know the difference between
what's real and what's not.
What we say is the truth,
everybody accepts, right, Owen?
I mean, psychiatry,
it's the latest religion.
We decide what's right and wrong,
we decide who's crazy or not.
I'm in trouble, here.
I'm losing my faith.
'You sure fucked up, Bob.
'But I can understand.
'You don't want your mistakes
pointed out to you.
'I can relate to that, old Bob.
'Yeah, I know what you're thinking.
'You're thinking I don't exist
except in your head.
'I can see that point of view.
'But you could still talk to me,
couldn't you?'
I saw you.
In 1996. In the real world.
- You'd pulled out your teeth.
- 'Why would I pull out my teeth, Bob?
'That's a no-no.
'And when did you say you saw me?
In 1872?'
Leave me alone!
'Yelling won't get you what you want.
'You have to be smart
to get what you want.'
- What do I want?
- 'You don't know what you want?
'Sure you do, Bob.
'You know what you want.'
You tell me.
You tell me what I want.
'To see the skies and the ocean.
'To be topside.
'To breathe the air.
'To be with... her.
'Isn't that right?
'Isn't that what you want... Bob?'
Yeah, hello?
Dr Railly, Jim Halperin. Philly PD.
I'm sorry to call you so early
this morning.
You found him? Is he OK?
No, no. Au contraire, Doctor.
No sign of your friend, the kidnapper.
However, the plot does thicken.
I got a ballistics report here
and it says the bullet you claim
you removed from Mr Cole's thigh
is, in fact, an antique.
'And all indications are
it was fired sometime prior to 1920s.
- 'What I'm thinking...'
- This can't be.
...you and I could grab a bite to eat,
then you can revise your statement.
Dr Railly?
No!
'You can't trick us, you know.
It wouldn't work.'
No, sir.
'You haven't become addicted,
have you, Cole, to that dying world?'
No, sir.
I just wanna do my part to get us
back on top, in charge of the planet.
And I have the experience,
I know the people involved.
He really is the most qualified.
But all that "behaviour".
You said we weren't real, Cole.
I don't think the human mind
is meant to exist in two different, er...
...whatever you call it,
dimensions?
It's too stressful.
You said that yourself.
It's very confusing. You don't know
what's real and what's not.
- But you know what's real now?
- Yes, sir. I do.
No, no, I don't know anything
about monkey armies, Doctor.
No, no, no.
Nothing whatsoever.
Good Lord, if my son was ever
involved in something like that...
Yes, well, I'm sorry,
I think it's doubly inappropriate
to discuss security matters
with you, Dr, er... Railly.
But, if it will ease your mind,
rest assured that neither my son
nor any other unauthorised person
has access to potentially dangerous
organisms in my laboratory.
Is that clear to you now, ma'am?
Thank you so much for your concern.
Women psychiatrists!
I attended a lecture of hers once.
"Apocalyptic Visions".
Yes, she was, er...
suddenly struck by the most
preposterous notion about Jeffrey.
Has she succumbed to her own...
theoretical Cassandra disease?
Maybe we ought to review
our security procedures.
Perhaps upgrade them.
Beef them up.
Let's consider again
our current information.
If the symptoms were first detected
in Philadelphia
on December 27, 1996,
that makes us know that...?
It was released in Philadelphia
probably on December 13, 1996.
And was seen sequentially
after that in...?
San Francisco, New Orleans,
Rio de Janeiro, er...
Rome, Kinshasa,
Karachi, Bangkok, then Peking.
That was very well done, Cole.
Hello! Is somebody in there?
If you're in there, I have to talk to you!
It's the kidnap woman,
who was with the guy who tied us up.
Turn off the lights. Turn off the lights!
- What's she doing?
- Drawing attention to us.
I don't know what you're up to
this time, Goines,
but you're gonna get us in deep shit.
Walkies ready? Batteries charged?
I saw you!
I saw somebody in there!
Secret experiments.
That's what they do.
Secret, weird stuff.
- Not just on animals.
- I know you.
- They do them on people, too.
- Have you seen James Cole?
They're watching you, taking pictures.
The police. I know. Look...
I have to contact James.
It's very, very important
that he's really careful when
he reaches me. Do you understand?
Yeah. Who's James?
He was with me.
He spoke to you, several weeks ago.
He said you were from the future
and you were watching him!
Bolt cutters. Bolt cutters.
- Did you get the bolt cutters?
- One dozen. They're in the van.
- Got the plans for the security system?
- All right here. Committed to memory.
Hey!
You know what she's doing out there?
- What's it say?
- Dunno. I can't see it.
Why don't we forget my psychiatrist
and concentrate on the task in hand?
Your psychiatrist?
Did you just say "your psychiatrist"?
Ex-psychiatrist.
This woman was your psychiatrist and
now she's spray-painting our building?
Kathryn?
James?
James!
There's policemen over there.
Pretend you don't know me.
No, I wanna turn myself in.
Where is he?
James! Down! Come on.
No, no, it's OK.
I'm not crazy any more.
I mean, I am.
I'm mentally divergent. I know that now.
I want you to help me.
I wanna get better. I wanna get better.
James!
Let's get outta here.
He's going. He's going.
- I've seen that before.
- No, James, you haven't.
A guy in a Ford is chasing her
and some other guy.
No problem.
It's probably just another kidnapping
featuring Jeffrey's shrink.
Pardon me, make that ex-shrink.
This is your leader?
A certifiable lunatic
who told his former psychiatrist
all his plans for God-knows-what
wacko irresponsible schemes?
God knows what she's written
on that wall!
Who cares what psychiatrists
write on walls?
You think I told her about
the Army of the Twelve Monkeys?
Impossible! Do you know why?
Do you know why?
Because, you pathetically ineffectual,
pusillanimous pretend friend to animals,
when I had anything to do with her
six years ago there was no such thing!
- I hadn't even thought of it yet.
- How come she knows what's going on?
Well, see, here's my theory on that:
When I was institutionalised,
my brain was studied exhaustively
in the guise of mental health.
I was interrogated, I was X-rayed,
I was examined thoroughly.
Then they took everything about me
and put it into a computer
where they created
this model of my mind.
Yes, using that model,
they managed to generate
every thought I could possibly have
in the next, say, ten years,
which they then filtered through
a probability matrix of some kind
to determine everything
I was gonna do in that period.
So you see, she knew I was gonna lead
the Army of the Twelve Monkeys
into the pages of history
before it ever even occurred to me.
She knows everything
I'm ever gonna do
before I know it myself.
How's that?
Kweskin, you finish here.
I'll meet you there.
If you forget one thing, I will have you
shaved, sterilised and destroyed.
- Jeff.
- What?
You're a great man.
Ah, fuck the bozos!
He's seriously crazy.
You know that.
'On the lookout
for two distinct persons
'by the names of Cole and Railly...'
There. Over there.
Come on.
- I need a room.
- Thirty-five bucks an hour.
An hour?
You want quarter hours,
go some place else.
Uh, here's...
Twenty, five, six, seven.
For an hour. Deal?
One hour, honey babe.
Number 64, sixth floor.
Up the stairs, end of the hall.
Elevator's busted.
She's not honey babe.
She's a doctor.
My psychiatrist. Understand?
Whatever gets it up for you, Jack.
Tommy? This is Charlie
over at the Globe.
You know if Wallace has a new girl?
Sort of a rookie type, a little weird.
Does fantasy acts.
OK, you were standing there,
looking up at the moon.
You were splashing
through the water and then what?
I thought I was in prison again.
Just like that, you were in prison?
No, not really.
Like you said,
it was all in my mind.
You disappeared, OK?
One minute you were there,
the next minute you were gone.
Did you run through the woods?
I don't know, I...
I don't remember.
The boy in the well.
How did you know
that was just a hoax?
It was?
- I didn't know.
- You said he was hiding in the barn.
I think I maybe saw
a TV show about that
when I was a kid, where a boy...
It wasn't a TV show, it was real!
Well, maybe this boy saw
the same TV show that I did
and he copied it.
Look, you... You were right.
I am mentally ill.
I imagined all these things,
these people.
- No...
- I... I know they're not real.
I can trick them.
I can make them do what I want.
I worked on them a little bit
and I got back here.
I'll get better. I can stay here.
This. What does this mean to you?
I think I had a dream... about this.
You had a... You had a bullet
from World War I in your leg, James.
- How did it get there?
- I don't know. Look, you said...
You said that I had delusions,
that I created this world.
- You said you could explain everything.
- I can't!
I'm trying to and...
I can't believe everything we say or do
has already happened,
that we can't change
what's gonna happen
and that five billion people
are gonna die!
I want the future to be unknown.
I want to become
a whole person again.
I want this to be the present.
I want to stay here, in this time...
with you.
James...
Do you remember six years ago,
you had a phone number?
- It was the wrong number then.
- A woman answered.
It was the wrong number in 1990.
It should be the right number now.
Do you remember it?
The number. Do you?
This is my territory, bitch!
- Is this real or one of my delusions?
- This is definitely real.
Uh, excuse me,
I think we've got
a little misunderstanding here.
Yeah. We...
Gee, really?
Now, you just sit tight, chief.
You listen to me,
Little Miss Understanding.
If you think you can go around me
and peddle your fancy ass
this part of town,
you bet your life we got
what I would call
a major fucking misunderstanding.
Oi!
James, no! Don't! Stop!
Uh... put him in the closet.
But take his money first.
- You want me to rob him?
- We need cash, James.
- Go!
- Fight! Call the cops! Call the cops!
What's going on?
I got friends, man.
You tried to kill me...
James? James!
No! James! Don't!
No, James! No!
No, open the door!
What the fuck are you doing?
Please don't hurt him.
Open the door! James, come on.
Just in case...
Just in case I'm not crazy.
This is how they find us,
by our teeth.
I don't want them to find me, ever.
- I don't wanna go back.
- James...
Oh, hi, boys.
Step back!
You'd better load.
Police!
Throw your weapons out
and come on out.
Hey, is that the cops?
Hey, I'm the innocent victim here.
I was attacked
by a coked-up whore
and a fucking crazy dentist!
Try to blend in.
Oh, Jesus!
Come on.
There's gotta be a phone
around here somewhere.
There. Over there, look.
- I'm gonna try that number, OK?
- OK.
- Let's just... Let's hope it's nothing.
Oh, my God!
James!
James! It's OK.
We're insane. We're crazy.
It's a carpet cleaning company!
- A carpet cleaning company?
- Yeah, no superiors.
No... no scientists,
no men from the future.
It's just a carpet cleaning company.
You leave a voicemail message
telling them when you want
your carpet cleaned.
- You left them a message?
- Yeah, I couldn't resist.
Wait till they hear this nutty woman
telling them to watch out
for the Army of the Twelve Monkeys!
I said, "The Freedom for Animals
Association..."
"...on 2nd Avenue
is the secret headquarters
"of the Army of the Twelve Monkeys.
"They're the ones
who are gonna do it.
"I can't do anything more now.
I have to go.
"Have a merry Christmas."
You couldn't have heard me.
They got your message, Kathryn.
They played it for me.
It was a bad recording, distorted.
I didn't recognise your voice.
This.
And this.
Is everything OK?
You want anything?
- Shall I put this on your account?
- Uh, no.
That'll... be cash.
And can you tell me
what floor the wigs are on?
He turned the thing
into a fucking computer.
- And Fale believed it?
- You know Fale.
He was like, "If you guys get nailed,
which I'm pretty sure you will,
"I've never seen you before
in my fucking life!"
Ha-ha! Yeah.
OK, drive!
What's the harm
in opening up the bag?
His eyes are taped, right?
Right?
OK, OK.
Hello. Hello.
- Wanna hear the monkey speak?
- Yeah!
Jeffrey? Jeffrey, I know that's you.
- I recognise your voice.
- No, you don't.
I also know all about
your warped little plan.
That lady, your psychiatrist...
She told me. I didn't believe her.
It just seemed too crazy, even for you.
But just in case, I took steps
to make sure
you couldn't go through with it.
I don't have the code anymore, Jeffrey.
I don't have access to the virus.
I took myself out of the loop.
Too late!
We got plans for you, Dad. Yeah.
I never let myself believe it.
Now I know it's true.
- Jeffrey?
- Hm.
You're completely insane.
No, I'm not.
'Here's a cross section of one
of the old trees that's been cut down.'
'Here I was born...
'...and there I died.
'It was only a moment for you. You...
'You took no notice.'
- I think I've seen this movie before.
- Shh!
- When I was a kid, I saw it on TV.
- Don't talk.
I did see it before.
- 'The tall trees...'
- 'Have you been here before?'
- 'Yes.'
- 'When?'
- But I don't... recognise this bit.
- 'When were you born?'
'Long ago.'
'Where?'
What's the matter?
- 'Tell me. Madeleine, tell me.'
- 'No!'
It's just like
what's happening with us.
Like the past.
The movie never changes,
it... can't change, but...
every time you see it, it seems
different because you're different.
You see different things.
'Please don't ask me!'
If you can't change anything
because it's already happened,
you may as well smell the flowers.
What flowers?
- It's an expression.
- Shh!
'Promise me something.
Promise you won't ask me again.'
Kathryn...
Why are you doing this?
I wanna know why.
What if I'm wrong?
What if you're wrong?
What if I am crazy?
In a few weeks,
it will have started or it won't.
If there's still...
...football games and traffic jams,
TV shows and armed robberies,
we're going to be so glad
that we'll be thrilled to see the police.
'I'm responsible for you now.
'The Chinese say that
once you save a person's life,
'you're responsible for it forever...'
Do you have a plan?
'I have to know.'
'There's so little that I know.'
- You said you'd never seen the ocean.
- Shh!
Hurry up. Come on.
I'll bring you the bolt cutters.
Jeffrey?
You know I can't see. Where are we?
Jeffrey? Please!
Kathryn!
We have 9:30 reservations
for Key West.
I...
I, uh... just didn't recognise you.
Well, you look pretty different yourself.
It was always you.
In my dream.
It was al...
It was always you.
- I remember you like this.
- You do?
I felt I've known you before.
I feel like I've always known you.
I'm so scared!
- What time's your flight, friends?
- 9:30.
- Might be tight.
- Tight?
No, my watch says 7:30.
On your normal morning,
OK, plenty of time,
but today you gotta take into account
the Army of the Twelve Monkeys factor.
- What? What did you say?
- Twelve Monkeys, honey.
I guess you folks didn't turn on
your radio this morning.
Bunch of weirdos
let all the animals out of the zoo.
Then they locked this big-shot scientist
in one of the cages.
Scientist's own kid,
one of the ones that did it.
Now they got animals
all over the place.
Bunch of zebras closed down
the Thruway about an hour ago.
And something called an emu,
it's got traffic blocked
for miles up on 676.
'...by releasing
an animal like this one
'into a city like this...'
That's what they were up to,
freeing animals!
On the walls it said, "We did it."
They meant the animals.
The animals. Yeah.
I think it's gonna be all right.
Tell your people
if they spot either one of them
not to try and apprehend them
but to notify us.
We have people all over the airport.
We'll take care of it.
- I know this place.
- Airports all look the same.
This is my dream.
- Your moustache.
- It's not just my dream.
I was actually here. I remember now.
About a week or two before the...
before everyone started dying.
Careful, they might be looking for us.
I was here.
- As a kid.
- Use this.
I think you were here then too.
James, if they identify us,
they're going to send us some place
but it won't be Key West.
- OK.
- I'll... I'll go fix this.
I'm gonna go get the tickets.
I'll meet you in the newspaper stand.
- OK.
Judy Simmons.
I have reservations for Key West.
'Flight 623 to Minneapolis
is now boarding at gate 44.'
- Don't see a lot of this. It's cash.
- It's a long story.
They'll begin boarding
in about 20 minutes.
- Have a nice flight, Miss Simmons.
- Thank you.
Hello. How are you today? Good.
I don't know
whether you're there or not.
Maybe you just clean carpets.
If you do, you're lucky.
You're gonna live a long, happy life.
But if you other guys are out there,
picking this up,
forget about the Army
of the Twelve Monkeys.
They didn't do it. It was a mistake.
Someone else did.
The Army of the Twelve Monkeys
is a bunch of dumb kids
playing revolutionaries.
Listen, I've done my job.
I did what you wanted.
Good luck. I'm not coming back.
Woo-ee! San Francisco,
New Orleans, Rio de Janeiro,
Rome, Kinshasa, Karachi,
Bangkok and Peking.
That's some trip you're taking, sir.
- Is this all in one week?
- Business.
Have a good one, sir.
'This is an information
announcement.
'Any luggage found unattended
will be removed and destroyed.'
Got yourself a prob, Bob?
Leave me alone! I made a report.
I didn't have to do that.
Point of fact, you don't belong here.
It's not permitted to let you stay.
This is the present.
This is not the past,
this is not the future.
This is right now!
I'm not leaving! You got that?
You can't stop me!
Anything you say, chief.
It's none of my business.
- Hey, Cole.
- What?
- Leave me alone!
- Calm down, Cole. It's me.
Cole, it's me.
- Jose?
- Yeah, right. Jose.
Hey, why did you pull out
the tooth, man?
That was nuts.
- Here, take this.
- What? What for?
- Are you crazy?
- Me? Are you kidding?
You're the one.
You were a hero, man.
They gave you a pardon and
you come back and fuck with your teeth.
- How did you find me?
- The phone call, man. The phone call.
They did their reconstruction thing on it.
The phone...?
The phone call I just made
five minutes ago?
Five minutes ago, 30 years ago.
They just put it together.
"Uh, hey. This is Cole, James.
"I don't know whether you're there.
Maybe you just clean carpets."
Where did you get that from?
"Forget about the Army
of the Twelve Monkeys."
Man, if only they could've got
your message earlier.
Here, you could still be a hero
if you just cooperate.
Come on, James. It's OK.
- That's $6.50. Here's your change.
- Thank you.
'Flight 784 for San Francisco
is now ready for boarding at gate 38.
is now ready for boarding.'
Oh, my God!
I got orders. Know what I'm supposed
to do if you don't go along this time?
- Shoot the lady.
- What?
Yeah. They said,
"If Cole don't obey orders..."
I'll break your fucking neck!
You hear me?
'Volunteers
now boarding at gate 37.'
You see? I had no choice.
These are my orders, man.
Just take it. Take it!
This part isn't about
the virus at all, is it?
It's about following orders,
about doing what you're told.
Hey, man, you got a pardon.
What do you want?
Hey, who am I supposed to shoot?
Who am I supposed to shoot?
James! It's Dr Goines' assistant.
He's an apocalypse nut.
I saw him a minute ago.
I think he's involved.
The next flight leaves from gate 38.
If he's there, I'm sure he's part of it.
Mr Holden, do you wanna
have a look at this, please?
Excuse me, sir. Let me have a look
at the contents of your bag, please.
Me?
We don't have time for this.
Excuse me.
Biological samples.
I have the papers right here.
Well, I'm gonna have to ask you
to open this up, sir.
Open it?
Why, yes, of course.
What could be better?
Come on, look at the planes. Hurry up.
- Excuse me.
- Ma'am, you'll have to get in the line.
You see?
Biological. Check the papers.
It's all proper. I have a permit.
It's empty.
Well, yes, to be sure,
it looks empty but...
...I assure you it's not.
- You don't understand.
- I don't have to.
No, this is very important.
There's a man. He's got red hair.
He's carrying a deadly virus.
There. You see?
Also invisible to the naked eye.
It doesn't... even... have an odour.
That's not necessary, sir.
There you go.
Thank you for your cooperation.
Have a good flight.
Yeah.
- Who are you calling a moron?
- I am calling you a fucking moron!
- Fucking moron!
- Get your hands off her!
Hold it! Wait a moment.
- She's not a criminal.
- Now, get in line.
You called me a fucking moron!
- You're not getting through.
- Let's go, lady.
I said stop!
- Ma'am, follow me.
- She's a psychiatrist!
There he is!
That man is carrying a deadly virus.
Stop him!
Somebody please stop him!
Police officer...
Watch it!
No!
Police! Freeze!
Excuse me.
It's obscene,
all the violence, all the lunacy.
Shootings even at airports now.
One might say that
we're the next endangered species.
Human beings.
I think you're right. Ma'am.
I think you've hit the nail on the head.
Jones is my name.
I'm in insurance.